Guide to the Lavoisier Manuscripts and Graphics Collection, circa 1750-1834 (bulk)
Lavoisier Manuscripts and Graphics Collection, circa 1750-1834 (bulk)
- Series VIIIA. Photocopies of documents held at other repositories
  - Eleutherian Mills Historical Library
    - Documents concerning the printing of assignats, 1792-1815 (Box 49, Folder 12)
      Physical Description: 14 leaves; 36 cm. or smaller.
    - Manuscript on the refinement of saltpeter (Box 49, Folder 13)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 36 cm. Draft in English, with revisions.
    - Manuscript on the affinities of saline substances (Box 49, Folder 14)
      Physical Description: 3 leaves; 36 cm. Draft with extensive revisions in two different hands.
    - Antoine Laurent Lavoisier: death sentence and confiscation of property (documents), 1794-1799 (Box 49, Folder 15)
      Physical Description: 18 leaves; 36 cm. or smaller.
    - Review of Richard Kirwan's Of the strength of acids in French translation by Mme. Lavoisier (Box 49, Folder 16)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 31 cm. Draft review of Mme. Lavoisier's translation. Unsigned, with revisions.
    - Notes from Lavoisier to Condorcet, 1791 (Box 49, Folder 17)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 28 cm.
      Summary: Notes from Lavoisier to Condorcet, dated July 28 and October 24, 1791. The first note concerns a letter by Lord Stanhope which Mr. Dupont and the Commissioner of the National Treasury would like to have printed in 500 copies. The second note instructs Condorcet to send the copies to Mr. Collin at the Treasury "for greater security."
    - Gunpowder (essay) (Box 49, Folder 18)
      Physical Description: 12 leaves; 36 cm. Fair copy, in English.
  - Archives nationales and other French archives
    - Documents, file F7 on Paulze's prosecution et al. (transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 19a)
      Physical Description: ca. 50 leaves; 27 cm
      Summary: Documents concerning the charges against Mme. Lavoisier's father, Mme. Lavoisier's interactions with the revolutionary government, and the dispersal of Lavoisier's scientific instruments and manuscripts.
    - Documents on "Citoyenne Lavoisier" (transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 19b)
      Physical Description: ca. 20 leaves; 27 cm
    - Documents, no. 570, on property of Emilie Punctis (transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 19c)
      Physical Description: ca. 40 leaves; 27 cm
      Summary: Posthumous inventory of the possessions of Lavoisier's mother, Emilie Punctis.
    - Documents on Lavoisier's library and his prosecution (transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 19d)
    - Documents from various French archives(transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 20a)
      Summary: Notes on a history of the Académie des sciences, on Lucien Scheler's book Lavoisier et la Révolution française, et al.
    - Documents from Archives de la Seine(transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 20b)
      Physical Description: ca. 30 leaves; 27 cm
      Summary: Documents on the dispersal of Lavoisier's possessions, including a house on the Rue des Bons Enfants.
    - Documents from the Archives nationales on Lavoisier's prosecution, file W521 (transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 21a)
    - Documents on Lavoisier's prosecution, file W362 no.785 (transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 21b)
    - Documents on Lavoisier's property, file A.B. XIX(transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 22a)
      Physical Description: ca. 20 leaves (typewritten); 27 cm
    - Documents on Lavoisier's prosecution, file F7 (transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 22b)
      Physical Description: ca. 30 leaves (typewritten); 27 cm
    - Documents on Lavoisier's prosecution, file F17 (transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 22c)
    - Documents on Lavoisier's prosecution, files M.C. Etude XCIX et al. (transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 22d)
      Physical Description: ca. 60 leaves (typewritten); 27 cm
      Summary: Includes detailed lists of documents and communications to, from, or about Lavoisier or Mme. Lavoisier from 1766-1781 and ca. 1795-1807.
    - Inventory of Lavoisier's library, files M. 795 and 796 (transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 22e)
    - Documents of Me. Gondouin on Lavoisier's property, file Me. Gondouin XCIX (transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 23a)
    - Documents of Me. Gondouin, germinal-prairial an IV (transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 23b)
      Physical Description: ca. 100 leaves; 27 cm
      Summary: Posthumous inventory of Lavoisier's possessions.
    - Documents of Me. Gondouin: posthumous inventory of Lavoisier's property (transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 23c)
      Physical Description: ca. 80 leaves; 27 cm
      Summary: Additional documents from prairial an IV on the posthumous inventory of Lavoisier's possessions.
    - Documents on dispersal of Lavoisier's property, file F17.1337 (transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 24a)
      Physical Description: ca. 70 leaves; 27 cm
    - Documents on the property of Lavoisier and Paulze, file F17 (transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 24b)
    - Inventory of Lavoisier's maps and plans, file F17.1052 (transcripts) (Box 49, Folder 24c)
      Physical Description: 9 leaves; 27 cm
- Series IX. Plates made by Marie Anne Lavoisier for the Traité élémentaire de chimie, 1789
  - Planche I
    - 5 original folders entitled as follows: (Box 13, Folder A)
      "Planches gravées par madame Lavoisier et représentant des appareils de chimie. Dessins et décalques ayant servi à l'exécution des ces planches"
      "Provenant de Lavoisier. Gravures représentant des figures de géométrie ou des instruments de chimie et de physique et se rapportant aux Mémoires de l'Académie des sciences."
      "Tableaux se rapportant à l'étude la chimie et à l'étude de la physique provenant probablement de Lavoisier"
      "Gravures représentant une expérience faite au moyen d'une grande loupe à la confection de laquelle Lavoisier avait participé"
      "Dessins et planches concernant un appareil pour la conservation des grains. Ces pièces proviennent très probablement de Lavoisier"
    - Planche I: preliminary print (Box 13, Folder 1)
      Abstract: Illustrations only, no numbers, letters or annotations.
      Physical Description: Print
    - Planche I: preliminary print (Box 13, Folder 2)
      Abstract: "Planche 1re" handwritten top left corner. No other annotations, no numbers or letters.
    - Planche I: preliminary print (Box 13, Folder 3)
      Abstract: "Planche 1re" handwritten top left corner, crossed out; "Planche 1ere" handwritten top right corner. Annotated in ink with all figure numbers and letters; Fig.13: "les trous doivent être égaux/les bords trop épais"; Fig.15 H: "les bords trop épais"
    - Planche I: preliminary print (Box 13, Folder 4)
      Abstract: "Planche I" handwritten top right corner. All figure numbers and letters annotated in ink in tid writing; "Paulze Lavoisier Sculpsit." bottom right corner.
      Physical Description: Print on green paper
    - Planche I: proof (Box 13, Folder 5)
      Abstract: All numbers, letters and corrections included. "Bonne" and initials at bottom right side.
    - Planche I: final proof (Box 13, Folder 6)
      Abstract: Complete as in final edition.
  - Planche II
    - Planche II: preliminary drawings (Box 14, Folder 1)
      Abstract: "Planche II" and "filtration" and "1ere" written in pencil, top right. Pencil sketches retraced in ink for definition and shading. Top row L-R Fig. 5, Fig 7, Fig.8 (green and grey paint); centre Fig.1 without cutaway (brown and grey paint; below Fig 3 (light yellow paint) with preliminary pencil-only sketches for Fig. 3 and Fig. 4.
      Physical Description: Sketch - pencil, ink, and watercolour
    - Planche II: preliminary drawings (Box 14, Folder 2)
      Abstract: "Evaporation" and "Planche II" written in pencil, top right. Pencil sketches retraced in ink for definition and shading. Clockwise from top left, glass and other vessels eventually to become Fig. 16, Fig. 4 F, an unidentified small round bowl (green paint); Fig. 15 (pink paint); Fig. 1 A (light brown paint); Fig 13 (pink paint), Fig 2 A (green paint). Two pencil-only sketches below: preliminary drawings for a structure resembling Fig. 4 and Fig 1A.
    - Planche II: preliminary drawings (Box 14, Folder 3)
      Abstract: "Planche II" and "Lixiviation" written in pencil, top right. Pencil sketches retraced in ink for definition and shading. Top Fig.12 (yellow, brown and grey paint); bottom preliminary Fig. 11 (green and grey paint) with top vase resting on a pedestal, ABCH drawn without hook at H, drizzle of liquid coming out at C.
    - Planche II: preliminary print (Box 14, Folder 4)
      Abstract: No numbers, letters, or annotations.
    - Planche II: preliminary print (Box 14, Folder 5)
      Abstract: "Planche II" written in ink top right. No numbers or letters; no further annotations.
    - Planche II: preliminary print (Box 14, Folder 6)
      Abstract: "planche 2e" written top left corner with strikethrough; "Planche II" written top right corner. Ink annotations of numbers and letters of figures. Annotations as follows: Fig. 10 "la base du verre est trop petite"; Fig. 4 F "mettre au milieu"; Fig 11 C "effacer le bout du tube". Adjustment of tube at Fig 11 I (not in final version).
    - Planche II: proof (Box 14, Folder 7)
      Abstract: Numbers and letters added; no annotations. Slight imperfection at Fig 4 F on rim of bowl (back leg of table still visible).
    - Planche II: proof (Box 14, Folder 8)
      Abstract: Complete with numbers and letters. Still a slight imperfection at Fig 4 F on rim of bowl.
    - Planche II: final proof. (Box 14, Folder 9)
      Abstract: "Bonne" written bottom right with initials in ink.
  - Planche III
    - Planche III: preliminary print (Box 15, Folder 1)
      Abstract: No numbers or letters or annotations.
    - Planche III: preliminary print (Box 15, Folder 2)
      Abstract: "Planche III" written top right in ink. No numbers or letters or further annotations.
    - Planche III: preliminary print (Box 15, Folder 3)
      Abstract: "Planche III" hand written top right corner. Annotations in ink. Figure numbers 1-7 added, Fig. 5 A C added (reverse to final copy). Fig. 6 with reference to neck of glass container "le col est trop long"; Fig.9 (unnumbered) "un petit trou", added "t" and dot on vessel represented.
    - Planche III: preliminary print (Box 15, Folder 4)
      Abstract: "PLANCHE III" written in ink top right. All figure numbers and letter added; Fig. 6 unfixed; hole drawn next to "t" on Fig. 9; Fig. 8 "les points un peu plus marqués. "Paulze Lavoisier Sculpsit" hand written bottom right.
    - Planche III: proof (Box 15, Folder 5)
      Abstract: Complete with numbers and letters, fixed neck of bottle on Fig. 6 and hole at T on Fig. 9; Fig. 8 "marquer un peu plus les points"; "Bonne" and initials at bottom right.
    - Planche III: final proof (Box 15, Folder 6)
      Abstract: Complete as in final edition
    - Planche III: final proof (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Planche IV
    - Planche IV: preliminary drawing (Box 16, Folder 1)
      Physical Description: Pencil sketch on printed graphed paper (18 x 29 squares)
    - Planche IV: preliminary print (Box 16, Folder 2)
      Abstract: Print with numbers, letters and heavily annotated in ink. "Planche IV." written top right corner, figure numbers indicated in brown ink, letters in black. Fig. 17 missing: sketched in with pencil; Fig. 2 waterline in E drawn in ink with annotation "remonter la [?]; Fig. 3 A and D confused, K added at top, lettering around base confused; Fig. 4 cross-piece between y and x tubes indicated with "effacer la traverse", two annotations for D "la capsule manque" and capsule sketched in ink outside drawing; Fig. 5 letters B and F confused, annotation indicating both M and N reads "les tuyeaux ne sont pas assez gros." small rectangular piece of paper attached with pushpin overtop with tubes M/N sketched in pencil with "opaque" written in centre, verso has ink sketch of unidentifiable apparatus; Fig. 10 C annotated to flare upwards a little with annotation "le col [?] avec le vase" and "plus gros par en haut" in blacker ink; Fig. 11 centre letter changed to N; Fig. 12 left sac "beaucoup trop de liqueur dans la cornue"; thirteen slashes at bottom right of page.
    - Planche IV: preliminary print (Box 16, Folder 3)
      Abstract: Letters and numbers printed. Missing Fig 3 P and later corrections.
    - Planche IV: preliminary print (Box 16, Folder 4)
      Abstract: Letters and numbers printed with the following annotations in ink: Fig. 1 at y line in tube annotated "effacer la"; a' corrected to "a", z' z'' z''' all one ' off final version, all L's corrected to L' L'' L''' although these corrections do not appear in the final version; Fig. 3 P omitted, but sketched off the left side of the graphic with diagonal line heading off from printed E to written "E"; Fig. 5 C written in ink with "mettre un grand ["petit" is crossed out] c, auquel on renvoye dans la description", annotation for M and N (now made opaque) "ces tubes plus gros"; Fig. 17 A written in ink with "Il faut un A à la tête du bouchon"; scratches at bottom centre now visible.
    - Planche IV: final proof. (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Planche V
    - Planche V: preliminary drawings (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Planche V: preliminary print (Box 16, Folder 7)
      Abstract: "Planche V" written in ink top right corner. Ink annotations of numbers and letters of figures. Fig 9 E written beneath handle. Annotation on Fig.11 "Le robinet ne doit point être arrondi par le bout"
    - Planche V: preliminary print (Box 16, Folder 8)
      Abstract: "PLANCHE V" written in ink top right corner. Ink annotations of numbers and letters of figures. Fig 9 E written beneath handle and scratched out to be placed above.
    - Planche V: preliminary print (Box 16, Folder 9)
      Abstract: Numbers and letters added. Ink annotation Fig. 10, line added from m trailing down to bottom of page, with annotation "Il faut "effacer cette m qui à été omise pour l'impression": this is all struck out with curly line. "Bonne" and initials at bottom centre.
    - Planche V: final proof (Box 16, Folder 10)
      Abstract: Numbers and letters added. Tap of Fig. 11 modified from rounded to square with some scratch marks visible.
  - Planche VI
    - Planche VI: preliminary drawings (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Planche VI: preliminary print (Box 17, Folder 2)
      Abstract: "Planche VI" written in upper right corner. Ink annotations indicating numbers and letters. Three ink strokes at bottomright.
    - Planche VI: preliminary print (Box 17, Folder 3)
      Abstract: Numbers and letters added.
    - Planche VI: final proof (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Planche VII
    - Planche VII: preliminary drawing (Box 17, Folder 5)
      Abstract: Drawn upside down on graph paper, bottom right corner red paper is fading from onionskin paper beneath.
    - Planche VII: preliminary print (Box 17, Folder 6)
      Abstract: Printed plate with ink annotations. "Planche VII" written in upper right corner.Numbers and some letters added to most figures. Fig. 5 what will become D is annotated "le haut plus marqué".
    - Planche VII: preliminary print (Box 17, Folder 7)
      Abstract: Letters and numbers added as indicated in previous plate. Annotations as follows: Fig. 2 A "mieux effacer le tube"; Fig. 4 indicated; lettering added on Fig. 5 and D is outlined more strongly as per previous instructions; Fig. 11 add K and S'; Fig. 6, 14 and 15 "Les lettres sont à mettre sur la gravure"; Fig. 17 "Les lettres sont à mettre sur la gravure", crossed out indication of P, and "effacer" crossed out with regards to tip of A.
    - Planche VII: proof (Box 17, Folder 8)
      Abstract: Letters and numbers added; all changes as indicated on previous copies.
    - Planche VII: proof (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Planche VIII
    - Planche VIII: preliminary drawing (Box 18, Folder 1)
      Abstract: All elements in place in their final version location. Carefully delineated, chiaroscuro rendering, some adjustments of positions of knobs and other devices in space. "Echelle" sketched at bottom.
      Physical Description: Pencil sketch on sketchbook paper
    - Planche VIII: wax tracing (Box 18, Folder 2)
      Abstract: Used twice for both versions of this plate: correction can be seen at gazometer hand indicator.
      Physical Description: Wax tracing
    - Planche VIII: copper plate (Box 29)
      Abstract: Original copper plate for engraving 18.3 with letters - hand of gazometer not fixed, first run of printing for this plate.
      Physical Description: Copper plate
    - Planche VIII: preliminary print (Box 18, Folder 3)
      Abstract: Ink markings for figure numbers and lettering, including numbers not included in final version. Handwritten: "Planche VII" and an annotation "pousser plus loin les traits de [?]" to modify the 'hand' labeled 30 between final proof letters m and E. Not the same amount of detail - cross-hatching and light lines. Piece between Fig.6 & 5 not shaded.
    - Planche VIII: preliminary print (Box 18, Folder 4)
      Abstract: Preliminary printing with annotated corrections (numbers and letters) added. Unmarked.
    - Planche VIII: preliminary print (Box 18, Folder 5)
      Abstract: Second printing; crosshatch repaired on G, parallel lines for shading on B; marker (formerly 30) between M and E size changed as noted. Annotated "Planche VIII" with final letters and numbers included.
    - Planche VIII: preliminary print (Box 18, Folder 6)
      Abstract: Shading on links between Fig. 6 and Fig. 5 intense.
    - Planche VIII: proof (Box 18, Folder 7)
      Abstract: Shading between Fig. 6 and Fig. 5 lessened.
    - Planche VIII: proof (Box 18, Folder 8)
      Abstract: Shading between Fig. 6 and Fig. 5 eliminated.
    - Planche VIII: final proof (Box 18, Folder 9)
      Abstract: Full engraving as printed in first edition. "Bonne" written in ink on bottom left and signed by Paulze Lavoisier.
  - Planche IX
    - Planche IX: preliminary drawings (Box 19, Folder 1)
      Abstract: "Combustion" and "Planche IX" written in pencil on right margin. Fig. 5 from Planche IX and an unidentified tubular glass with wick and flame inside. Colours are blue and grey with black and red, peach and yellow for flames.
    - Planche IX: preliminary drawings (Box 19, Folder 2)
      Abstract: Pencil sketch with chiaroscuro on Fig. 1, 3, 4 &5. Ink annotations indicating numbers and letters.
      Physical Description: Pencil sketch
    - Planche IX: preliminary print (Box 19, Folder 3)
      Abstract: No lettering or annotations. Bottom of Fig. 4 (between x and s) carved out.
    - Planche IX: preliminary print (Box 19, Folder 4)
      Abstract: Ink annotations as follows: "Planche IX" top right corner. Figure numbers and letters written in except for Fig. 5 (no letters). Annotations to Fig. 4: 1 and 2 "le rebord n'est pas assez marqué"; between s and x "noircir le bout des tuyeaux qui ne vont pas au fond. Continuer la ligne NO"; between 1 and 2 blank space with indication "ôter le fond en prolongeant les lignes"; blank space filled in with pencil marks to indicate continuing the background lines and eradicate white space.
    - Planche IX: preliminary print (Box 19, Folder 5)
      Abstract: "PLANCHE IX" in ink at top right corner. Ink annotations include all figure numbers and letters, "Echelle de cinq pieds" handwritten over scale at bottom centre; "Paulze Lavoisier sculpsit" bottom right corner; Fig. 4 single line between s and x to fill in straight line from N to O.
    - Planche IX: proof (Box 19, Folder 6)
      Abstract: All corrections made, all letters and numbers included.
    - Planche IX: final proof (Box 19, Folder 7)
      Abstract: "Bonne" and initials at bottom centre.
  - Planche X
    - Planche X: wax tracing (Box 20, Folder 1)
      Abstract: Clear outlines, no shading or detail.
    - Planche X: preliminary print (Box 20, Folder 2)
      Abstract: No numbers or letters, "Planche X" handwritten top right corner.
    - Planche X: preliminary print (Box 20, Folder 3)
      Abstract: "PLANCHE X" in ink at top right. Image printed with numbers and letters annotated in ink. Corrections of Fig. 1 h and t to different locations.
    - Planche X: preliminary print (Box 20, Folder 4)
      Abstract: "Planche X." in ink at top right. Image printed with numbers and letters annotated in ink.
    - Planche X: proof (Box 20, Folder 5)
      Abstract: "Bonne" and initials at bottom centre. Ink stain over right hand support poly (under i).
    - Planche X: proof (Box 20, Folder 6)
      Abstract: Numbers and letters printed. Rust stain at Fig. 1 p.
  - Planche XI
    - Planche XI: wax tracing (Box 20, Folder 7)
      Abstract: Clear outlines, no shading or detail: apparatus on bottom shelf as in 20.8 and as added later.
    - Planche XI: preliminary drawings (Box 20, Folder 8)
      Abstract: Almost full experimental apparatus executed in lines of black ink, with watercolour in grey tones for shading, white for accenting and correcting. Piece glued on over left leg and corner of P, also bottom right of table runner as corrections. a is drawn in pencil. Bottom shelf of table has instruments of various kinds on it not included in final print. Extra sketchings erased at bottom centre of drawing: scale sketched in pencil at bottom right. Framed with thick black ink line over pencil.
      Physical Description: Sketch - pencil, ink, and watercolour on green paper
    - Planche XI: preliminary print (Box 20, Folder 9)
      Abstract: Annotated in ink with numbers and letters. "Planche XI" in top right corner. Numbers 10-17 confused, locations of 19-30 corrected, moved from one location to another (i.e. outside the vessels to inside).
    - Planche XI: preliminary print (Box 20, Folder 10)
      Abstract: Annotated in ink with numbers and letters. "Pl XI" in top right corner.
    - Planche XI: proof (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Planche XI: proof (Box 20, Folder 12)
      Abstract: Print with letters and numbers engraved.
  - Planche XII
    - Planche XII: wax tracing (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Planche XII: preliminary print (Box 21, Folder 2)
      Abstract: Annotated in ink with numbers and letters. "Planche XII" in top right corner. Fig. 10 corrected to Fig. 11, Fig. 14 changed to 15, Fig. 17 changed to 18. Annotations as follows: Fig. 17 B: "opaque"; Fig. 16 A B C redrawn with annotation "le tube plus petit", "une marque" added at C; Fig. 12 B "échancrures"; Fig. 15 I K "la lame platte".
    - Planche XII: preliminary print (Box 21, Folder 3)
      Abstract: Annotated in ink with numbers and letters in adjusted places. "12" in pencil in top right corner. No further annotation.
    - Planche XII: preliminary print (Box 21, Folder 4)
      Abstract: Numbers and letters now printed except for Fig 18 hand-numbered and Fig. 8 corrections. Annotated in ink: Fig. 2 9 corrected "g au lieu de 9"; Fig. 8 lettering clarified; Fig. 9 letters o and e "Effacer ces deux lettres"; Fig. 18 "toutes les lettres de cette figure manquent"; Fig. 16 B C "effacer le faux trait" referring to the tube that is still not small enough (what was shading becomes the tube); Fig. 11 lettered and titled, Fig. 15 "Placer l'F un peu plus haut" I "la lame platte".
    - Planche XII: proof (Box 21, Folder 5)
      Abstract: Corrections from J-6 made. No annotations.
  - Planche XIII
    - Planche XIII: preliminary drawings (Box 21, Folder 6)
      Abstract: Original version sketch (no changes to openings, no annotations).
    - Planche XIII: preliminary print (Box 21, Folder 7)
      Abstract: No numbers or letters added.
    - Planche XIII: preliminary print (Box 21, Folder 8)